A Guide to the Rives Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10596-c
Rives Family Papers ca. 1832-1882
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10596-c
ca. 130 items
Laurens H. Rhinelander
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to the Library by Laurens H. Rhinelander of Charlottesville, Virginia, on December 30, 1985.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 130 letters, ca. 1832-1882, chiefly correspondence among members of the Rives family of " Castle Hill, " Cobham, Virginia. The main correspondents are William Cabell Rives(1793-1868), Judith Page Walker Rives(1802-1882), William Cabell Rives, Jr.(1825-1889), and Amelie Louise Rives Sigourney(1832-1873); other correspondents include Francis Robert Rives(1822-1891), Alfred Landon Rives(1830-1903), Ella Rives(1834-1892), John Reuben Thompson(1823-1873), and Fitzedward Hall(1825-1901).
Topics of interest include: Paris, France in 1832; sailing on the S.S. Arabic and visiting London, England, in 1860; the publication of William Cabell Rives'
History of the Life and Times of James Madison
personal and business affairs in Cobham; and, the Civil War and its effects.
William Cabell Rives' letters to his son during the late 1860's often refer to the publication of his three-volume work on James Madison, as well as William Cabell Rives, Jr.'s business affairs at Cobham.
Judith Page Walker Rives' letters discuss news of her family and friends. During 1865-1867, she expressed her opinions concerning the effects of the Civil War on blacks. On November 6, 1865, she mentions a "free negro settlement" in Cobham, and that Dr. Eastham has offered work to them. On January 15, 1866, she writes of the conditions and work relationships with blacks after the war. And, in her letters of March 9 and 19, and June 15, 1867, she expresses her displeasure at blacks receiving the right to vote while her husband and son, Alfred Landon, have been disenfranchised.
During 1860, William Cabell Rives, Jr., sailed on the S.S. Arabic, and wrote often to his wife, Grace, about life on the ship, the hardships and dangers, and the activities of fellow passengers. His letters are filled with gossip and descriptions of officers, sailors, and other passengers on board. In April and May of 1860, he writes of travelling in London, visiting the Speaker's Gallery in the House of Commons and hearing Sir Edward Bulwer-Lytton speak, and meeting members of the Royal Family. He gives lengthy descriptions of the Queen, Prince Albert, Princess Alice, and Princess Mary.
In 1863 and 1864, Francis Robert Rives wrote to his brother, William Cabell, from New York concerning Civil War news as reported there. His letters of January 10 and 12 mention the "great columns of Burnside," William S. Rosecrans and the battle of Murfreesboro, an expedition against Wilmington, N.C., a federal naval disaster at Galveston, the performances of the cruiser, Alabama, and England's reluctance to intervene on the Southern side. In his August 3, 1864, letter he mentions a letter from Grant's headquarters stating that two corps are embarking for Washington and Baltimore and of word that vessels are proceeding to Fort Monroe. And, on September 21, 1864, he indicates that a previously missing soldier, Eugene Davis, the son of Staige Davis, was a prisoner of war.
Other letters of interest include one of January 31, 1861, from John Reuben Thompson and one of May 5, 1861, from Fitzedward Hall to William Cabell Rives, Jr. From Richmond, Thompson writes of the current "condition of public affairs" due to the differences between the South and the Union, and the question of secession. Hall writes about living and working in Sangur, India, as the Inspector of Schools of Central India and formerly as an employee of the East India Company.
Organization
The material in this collection has been filed chronologically, with folders arranged by various correspondents.
Container List
- Judith Page Walker Rives to William Cabell Rives, Sr., 1832; ALS
- Miscellaneous correspondence of William Cabell Rives, Sr. and Judith Page Walker Rives, 1856, 1859; 2 ASsS
- Amelie Louise Rives Sigourney to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1857-1863; 7 ALsS
- Judith Page Walker Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1859-1860; 7 ALsS
- William Cabell Rives, Jr. to Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1860; 17 ALsS
- William Cabell Rives, Sr. to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1860-1868; 16 ALsS
- Letters between William Cabell Rives, Jr. Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, and William Cabell Rives (3rd), 1860-1868; 6 ALsS
- Letters of Introduction for William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1860-1873; 13 ALsS
- Letters to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1861-1880; 7 ALsS
- Francis Robert Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1863-1882; 9 ALsS
- Amelie Louise Rives Sigourney to William Cabell Rives, Jr. and Grace Winthrop Sears Rives, 1864-1865; 7 ALsS
- Judith Page Walker Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1865; 6 ALsS
- Judith Page Walker Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1866; 8 ALsS
- Judith Page Walker Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1867; 18 ALsS
- Judith Page Walker Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1875-1876; 3 ALsS
- Ella Rives to William Cabell Rives, Jr., 1878-1881; 6 ALsS